Today’s דף Daf is קד Kuf Daled 104,
and
we pick up
somewhere in the middle of
קג עמוד ב Kuf Gimmel Amud Bet where it
says מיתיבי, בית המוסגר. Meitivei Bayit Hamusgar.
It starts with מוסגר Musgar on the line there is a little
רש״י א Rashi Alef in parentheses. It's about 20 lines from the
bottom. מיתיבי Meitivei, בית המוסגר. Bayit Hamusgar. So the question here is
the statement about whether you can use a sandal that has been
had a צרעת Tzara'at on it. So if it’s only מוסגר, Musgar,
you’re determining its status, then it’s טמא, Tamei, but no reason you
can’t, בדיעבד Bedieved it’s not good. If it’s מוחלט, Muchlat, that means
its status has been finalized and it’s going to be
destroyed. So then is it an idea that something that's going to
be destroyed כיתותי מיכתת שיעוריה, Kitutei Mechatat Shiurei, it's like the
שיעור Shiur is already destroyed or the fact that it's going to
be destroyed enough undermines its importance and it doesn't satisfy a שיעור
Shiur requirement. And we never had a per se שיעור Shiur requirement,
it has to be 10 טפחים Tefachim or whatever like a quantitative
number, but it would maybe undermine its status as a shoe. It
can't be considered a significant shoe if it's something that's going to
be destroyed, and we'll see how the גמרא Gemara will use particularly
that idea of כיתותי מיכתת שיעוריה Kitutei Mechatat Shiurei here, that something
that's going to be destroyed loses its sort of identity as the
particular object as a functional object that it's supposed to be. So
that's the
debate. So רב פפי Rav Pappi said in the name of רבא
Rava said it's no good, and רב פפא Rav Pappa in the
name of רבא Rava said it is good. So let's take a
look. מיתיבי, Meitivei, says the גמרא, Gemara, asks you on this: בית
המוסגר, Bayit Hamusgar,
you have this issue about the house, the house is sealed up
and you're determining its status whether it's a צרעת Tzara'at or not,
מתוכו, Mitocho, it's טמא Tamei from
the inside. מוחלט, Muchlat, if the status has been finalized, it went
through the seven days and whatever the laws of צרעת Tzara'at are,
and its status is finalized and then you're going to also break
it down and destroy it, that's sort of on the agenda. So
then in that case מתוכו ומאחוריו Mitocho Umiachorav causes טומאה Tumah from
the inside and the outside, even if you just touch the outside.
Not only that, וזה וזה, Veze Veze, both of them מטמאין בביאה,
Metam'in Beviah, cause טומאה Tumah just by entering even without touching, because
it says הבא אל הבית. Haba El Habayit. All right, well, that
doesn't count. That doesn't count, you're not touching the walls of the
house. ואי סלקא דעתך כמיכתת דמי, Veisaka Daitech Kimechtat Damei, if you
say that something that's going to be destroyed is like it's already
ground up, דהא בעינן והבא אל הבית, Deha Beinan Vehabayit, how could
it still count as a house? So once it's מוחלט, Muchlat, it
shouldn't be טמא Tamei when you go into it because it's no
longer one who enters the house. How could it still have the
identity of a house like you're saying it doesn't have the identity
of a shoe? So שאני הכא דאמר קרא, Shani Hacha Damar Kra,
here the verse is different because it says ונתץ את הבית, Venatatz
Et Habayit, you shall destroy the house, level the house, אפילו בשעת
נתיצה קרוי בית, Afilla Besha'at Netitzah Karuy Bayit,
even when you're in the process of destroying it and leveling it,
it's still being called a house. So here the תורה Torah says
for the purposes of this הלכה Halacha we're going to continue to
recognize it as a house even once it's in the process of
being destroyed. Now of course it's also a good logic because like
internally within צרעת Tzara'at we will continue to recognize it as such.
But you go ahead and you want to use it for something
else, you want to use it for חליצה Chalitzah or you want
to talk about shoes instead of houses, that's a different story. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע, Tashma, come
and hear. מטלית, Matlit,
if you have a piece of a garment שיש בה שלש על
שלש, Sheyesh Bah Shalosh Al Shalosh, which is three finger widths wide
by three finger widths wide,
which defines it as a בגד. Beged. אף על פי שאין בה
כזית, Af Al Pi She'ein Bah Kezayit, even if it's a funny
phrase to use as a כזית Kezayit for clothes, we'll see why
that's significant, but even though it is not a כזית Kezayit if
you bunch it up and sort of see its volume it would
be less than a כזית, Kezayit, we'll get back to כזית Kezayit
in a second, but you have this piece of cloth. כיון שנכנס
רובו לבית טהור טימאהו. Keivan Shenichnas Rubo Leveit Tahor Tim'ahu.
Once the majority of it has gone into a טהור Tahor house,
this is a piece of cloth that has צרעת Tzara'at on it,
it's מנוגע, Menuga, it's got the צרעת Tzara'at so it causes טומאה.
Tumah. So the same way if you enter a house that has
צרעת Tzara'at you become טמא, Tamei, if you bring a מצורע Metzora
goes into a house or this בגד מצורע Beged Metzora enters into
a house, it makes the house טמא. Tamei. So it doesn't have
to be the whole thing, even the full שיעור Shiur of שלש
על שלש, Shalosh Al Shalosh, even though that's the minimum size you
need of the garment, you only need the majority of the garment
to go in even if that minimum size has not gone in.
כיון שנכנס רובו לבית טהור טימאהו, Keivan Shenichnas Rubo Leveit Tahor Tim'ahu,
it made it טמא. Tamei. מאי לאו, Mai Lav, are we not
talking about מוחלטת, Muchletet, that this is a garment that is מוחלט,
Muchlat, it's going to be destroyed, and nevertheless it's considered to be
a minimum size to cause טומאה? Tumah? Now of course, that's a
question, like, of course. One minute. Of course you need to maintain
the idea of a שיעור shiur once it's causing טומאה, tumah, because
then nothing will ever cause טומאה. tumah. You'll say, oh, well, it's
מוחלט, muchlat, then it's like it doesn't have a שיעור, shiur, so
it doesn't have a שיעור, shiur, can't cause טומאה, tumah, right? So
the גמרא Gemara isn't suggesting that. But the way רש״י Rashi explains
what the גמרא Gemara is suggesting it, is that the idea that
a part of the thing goes in is like the whole thing
goes in. That's a sense of a coherence of the object that
we're still looking at it as a בגד, beged, as a sort
of as a unified object. So until now we've even been saying,
מחצה שיעור mechtza shiur means we can't call it a shoe anymore.
מחצה שיעור mechtza shiur means we can't call it a house anymore.
But if you say מחצה שיעור mechtza shiur about this thing, you
can't see it as like a unified object. So yesterday as a
שיעור shiur if you touch it, you're טמא. tamei. But to say
it's the majority goes into the house, it's like the whole object
went into the house. No, we're trying to argue that מחצה שיעור
mechtza shiur loses its coherent identity as an object.
No longer the object.
Right. So that's true. Why do we say this? So aren't we
talking about something that's מוחלט, muchlat, that's going to be destroyed? לא,
Lo, מוסגרת. musgeret. No, מוסגר, musgar, that's not going to be destroyed.
אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, that's true, אימא סיפא.
eima seifa.
So therefore let's look at the end of this ברייתא. braita. היו
בו כמה זיתים, Hayu bo kama zeitim, if the piece of
garment, it's מטמא metamei everything else? We don't know. I mean, what's
the...
there's no... מוסגר musgar causes טומאה. tumah. It does. Yeah. Yeah. While
it's in this state of a בעינן, beinan, it causes טומאה, tumah,
you just don't have to destroy it yet. Right. That's true about
all this. I said that at the very beginning. Once something is
מוסגר, musgar, you know, it's מטמא. metamei. It's only מוחלט, muchlat, like
by a person, it means there's going to be a much longer
process of טהרה, tahara, and by the garment and the clothes, it
means you destroy them.
But what I don't understand is, how does it מטמא metamei the
house? In other words, צרעת הבית tzaraat habayit is different than צרעת
הבגד. tzaraat habeged.
I understand. That's one of the things I said, that if a
מצורע metzora goes into a house, he is מטמא metamei it. If
a בגד מצורע beged metzora enters into a house, it מטמא metamei
the house. That's one of the laws of צרעת. tzaraat. Next time
we learn נגעים, Negaim, we'll go through it, okay? But you'll just
have to accept that. All right. So now, now let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, let's אימא סיפא. eima
seifa. Let's look at the end. היו בו כמה זיתים. Hayu bo
kama zeitim. There was a very thick garment and its volume is
the size of a number of olives. כיון שנכנס ממנו כזית, Keivan
shenichnas mimenu kezayit,
once a כזית kezayit worth of the garment goes in, even if
it's not three by three, טימאהו לבית ההוא, timateihu labayit ha'u, it
makes it טמא. tamei.
Now what's the logic? We're going to see in a minute where
this idea of a כזית kezayit is coming from. אי אמרת בשלמא
מוחלטת, Ei amrat bishlama muchletet, if
we're talking about a מוחלט muchlat garment, so היינו דאיתקש למת, hainu
de-itkash le-meit, we understand this concept that a כזית kezayit causes טומאה
tumah of it, even though it's not normally a relevant size by
garment, because it's compared, because anything that has צרעת tzaraat is compared
because it's considered like a dead body. Right? When, you know, when
משה Moshe prays for מרים Miriam and says, אל נא תהי כמת
אשר בצאתו מרחם אמו ויאכל חצי בשרו. Al na tehi che-meit asher
bezeito me-rechem imo vay-achel chatzi besaro.
So therefore the idea that something with צרעת tzaraat is like a
מת meit has relevance for laws of טומאה, tumah, that even a
כזית kezayit of a garment, even though that's not normally a relevant
שיעור, shiur, causes טומאה. tumah. But that, the גמרא Gemara says, is
only, the גמרא Gemara assumes is only when it's in this מוחלט
muchlat status. Okay. So אי אמרת מוסגרת, ei amrat musgeret, so if
you say מוסגר, musgar, אמאי מטמא? amai metamei? I'm sorry, אמאי אמאי?
amai amai?
So why is it? So מוחלט muchlat we understand the idea of
כזית, kezayit, but not by מוסגר. musgar. So clearly we're talking about
מוחלט. muchlat. And even though we're talking about מוחלט, muchlat, we see
that the object has a sense of unity and coherence. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמאי איתקש למת? amai itkash le-meit?
Right, a מוסגר musgar isn't connected to a מת. meit. So the
גמרא Gemara says, you know what, you're right. שאני התם, Shani hatam,
you're right, forget it. רש״י Rashi adds in the word אלא. ela.
We're talking, we are talking about a מוחלט, muchlat, and that's why
כזית kezayit is relevant. How about the idea that even if a
part of the garment goes in, it has a whole coherence as
a unity? So שאני התם דאמר קרא ושרף את הבגד. Shani hatam
de-amar kra ve-saraf et habeged. Same thing we said before about the
house still being considered a house, the garment is still considered a
garment, אפילו בשעת שרפה קרוי בגד, afilu bish'at sreifa karui beged, even
when you're going to destroy it, it's going to be called a
בגד. beged. And as I should say, it's not just, oh, well,
it counts as a house and it counts as a garment, but
it doesn't count as a shoe. No, the part of the point
is that this is within the laws of צרעת, tzaraat, even though
the thing is a house to be destroyed. For laws of צרעת,
tzaraat, we're still calling it a house. And even though it's a
בגד beged going to be destroyed, for laws of צרעת, tzaraat, we're
still calling it a unified בגד. beged. It doesn't necessarily mean that
you can go ahead and use it for something else. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara one moment, the גמרא's Gemara going to ask that
question. So the גמרא Gemara says, וניגמור מינה. ve-nigmor mineh. Why not
say, oh, if that's true and it's still called a בגד beged
with צרעת, tzaraat, let's use it for חליצה. chalitza. The גמרא Gemara
says no, איסור מטומאה לא גמרינן. Issur mi-tumah lo gamrinan. We don't
learn איסור issur from טומאה. tumah. That's its own sort of
set of ritual rules. רש״י Rashi says the whole category of טומאה
tumah is a חידוש. chidush. So everything there is somewhat arbitrary. Okay,
and רש״י Rashi last narrow line of רש״י, Rashi, הלכות טומאה חידוש
הוא. hilchot tumah chidush hu. And therefore you cannot use that as
something that becomes as applied in other הלכה halachic categories. Right. The
point I would make is not just איסור issur and טומאה, tumah,
which would suggest like from טומאה tumah to טומאה tumah you could
learn it, but also one of the things to appreciate here is
that it's also this logic is only internal, that it's still considered
the object within the own laws that you're dealing with right now,
not again, not, you know... but the גמרא Gemara makes even a
broader statement that you don't apply טומאה tuma laws to other categories.
Yes, Michael. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, so
that's the position that בדיעבד bedieved is not good. The position that
בדיעבד bedieved is good, רבא Rava says, is presumably that you do
learn איסור issur from טומאה. tuma. Once you see that in a
case of צרעת tzaraat within laws of צרעת, tzaraat, it's considered to
have its object identity, so therefore for other laws as well it
has its object identity and you can use it for חליצה. chalitzah.
So that's the two versions of
רבא. Rava. Meaning anything that's not דיני ממונות. dinei mamonus. So anyway,
and that's not טומאה. tuma. So therefore, what do you call it?
So that's the debate of the two or that's the two versions
of רבא Rava whether you can use a סנדל המוקלט. sandal hamuklat.
So אמר רבא הלכתא, amar Rava hilchasa, now this is fascinating because
the discussion started with אמר רב פפי משמיה דרבא amar Rav Pappi
mishmei deRava and אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא, amar Rav Pappa mishmei
deRava, so there were two versions of רבא Rava and now we're
quoting רבא Rava directly. So why don't we just start with the
quote of רבא Rava directly? What, I mean, you know, anyway, like
didn't people... I don't know, anyway.
Didn't people pay attention in שיעור? shiur?
Exactly. אמר רבא הלכתא, amar Rava hilchasa, הלכה halachah is אחד סנדל
המוסקב ואחד סנדל המוקלט, echad sandal hamuskav ve'echad sandal hamuklat,
whether it is מוסקב muskav or מוקלט, muklat, it's going to be
okay. So this is basically the רב פפא Rav Pappa version. Okay,
ואחד סנדל המוקלט ואחד סנדל של עבודת כוכבים,
ve'echad sandal hamuklat ve'echad sandal shel
avodat kochavim,
and even a sandal that is of idolatry, like maybe you worship
the sandal, לא תחלוץ, lo tachlotz, you don't use it, ואם חלצה
ve'im chaltzah בדיעבד bedieved if you did, חליצתה כשירה, chalitzatah kesherah, it's
good. Okay, the one about leprosy we spoke about, that it still
has the identity of a בגד beged or of a sandal. The
עבודה זרה avodah zarah I'll talk about in a minute. שתקרובת עבודת
כוכבים, sheteikroves avodat kochavim,
if however it wasn't a sandal that was worshipped but it was
just something that was offered to an idol, right, it was placed
in front of an idol as a type of an offering, ושל
עיר הנדחת, veshel ir nidachas, and a city that is going to
be, you know, completely burned up. Okay, ושל זקן העשוי לכבודו, veshel
zakein ha'asui lichvodo, now this is a euphemism, זקן עשוי לכבודו zakein
asui lichvodo means it's for a מת, meis, it's like a booty
that you're going to put on a dead body. Shroud for a
foot. Yeah, I think so. And but it's not going to be
made for actual walking. לא תחלוץ, lo tachlotz, don't use it, ואם
חלצה חליצתה פסולה, ve'im chaltzah chalitzatah psulah, and if you did it's
בדיעבד bedieved not good. So we'll discuss the זקן zakein in a
minute. ועיר הנדחת ve'ir nidachas points to the idea that רבא Rava
says, I, you know, that in principle, of course, the idea of
כתותי מיכתת שיעוריה kitutei meichtas shiurei applies here. And if it is
something that is going to be destroyed, it, you know, outside of
the laws of צרעת, tzaraat, if צרעת tzaraat as we saw is
an exception, but put aside צרעת, tzaraat, if something's going to be
destroyed for another reason because it's like עיר הנדחת, ir nidachas, then
it cannot be used. Okay, that's good. So that's fine, we understand
that. So what's the difference then between עבודה זרה avodah zarah and
תקרובת עבודה זרה? tikroves avodah zarah? Both of those you're supposed to
destroy. Why can you use... why בדיעבד bedieved is one good and
one not good? Okay, everyone understand the question, right? So רבא Rava
gives no distinction. So רש"י Rashi says the difference is is that
if it was an עבודה זרה avodah zarah worshipped by a non-Jew,
then a non-Jew could be מבטל mevatel it. A non-Jew could say
I no longer believe in it and then it stops being עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. One minute. So but if it's an offering made
to an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it can never change its status.
So רש"י Rashi says the reason you can use the sandal of
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it's עבודה זרה avodah zarah of a non-Jew,
and the fact that it has the potential of losing its status
means we don't apply the principle of מכתת שיעוריה. meichtas shiurei. Of
course as long as he isn't מבטל mevatel it, I'm going to
go ahead and destroy it. But as long as... but as long
as I haven't in practice destroyed it and as long as it
has the potential of not being destroyed if he chooses to be
מבטל, mevatel, I won't say the principle of מכתת שיעוריה. meichtas shiurei.
But you'd say the same but even if he hasn't מבטל? mevatel?
Even if he has not been מבטל, mevatel, בדיעבד bedieved if I
used it, it's good. That's what רש"י Rashi says because it's not
מכתת שיעוריה. meichtas shiurei. Now you'll also say one minute, but didn't
you get הנאה hana'ah from עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? You use the
sandal of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, isn't it אסור assur to get
הנאה? hana'ah?
Right, exactly. So two lines from the bottom of רש"י ק"ז עמוד
ב', Rashi kuf-zayin amud bais, he says חליצה לאו הנאה היא דמצוות
לאו ליהנות ניתנו. chalitzah lav hana'ah hi demitzvos lav leihanos nitnu. The
fact that you use this right for חליצה chalitzah to do a
מצוה mitzvah is not a הנאה. hana'ah. Now this by the way
is interesting because it gets to a question which I'm going to
address again in a second, which is do we primarily look... it
gets to a question we was talking the other day, do we
primarily look at חליצה chalitzah as a מצוה? mitzvah? Check, I did
a nice מצוה, mitzvah, I shook the לולב lulav and I did
the shoe מצוה mitzvah too. Okay, so so that's one way of
looking at it. Other way of looking at it, I don't know,
do we look at גט get as a מצוה? mitzvah? No, maybe
we look at it as a type of a transaction that's done
to free this woman. It's not a מצוה mitzvah like like oh
שכר מצוה schar mitzvah doesn't count as הנאה. hana'ah. So I don't
know if it was a transaction, if I basically wrote my גט
get on איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, right, that's a question. Is that
okay? Does... I mean there's one question, is the גט get kosher,
but was I עובר over on the איסור issur of getting הנאה?
hana'ah? It saved me... it saved me from having to buy a
different cloth. I got some pragmatic benefit, you know, that I would...
you know, so so is that... is the woman... maybe the woman
gets benefit that she's freed, you know, that's not exactly the מצוות
לאו ליהנות ניתנו. mitzvos lav leihanos nitnu. So the fact is that
maybe we should... Or maybe you'll say that's not called הנאה hana'ah
either. Fine. But by framing it as מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו, mitzvot
lav lehennot nitnu, what רש"י Rashi is saying is our primary way
of looking at what's going on here is like a ritual קיום
מצווה, kiyom mitzvah, not a type of a transaction to free the
woman.
It's a קיום. kiyom. I understand. No, it's a יבום. yibbum.
Well you could do יבום. yibbum. You could do יבום. yibbum. I'm
not saying there isn't reasons to look at it that way, I'm
just saying that it's a חידוש. chiddush. You could have said this
is just a transaction. It's like when you do הגבהה. hagbahah. If
you want to own an object you would do הגבהה. hagbahah. If
you want to free the sister-in-law you do חליצה. chalitzah. So I
mean, so I think it's an interesting question, right, and רש"י Rashi
by one thing to ask yourself is do you make a ברכה
berakhah on חליצה? chalitzah? Right? So are we going to see that?
We haven't seen it yet. I'll let you think about that. So
okay, but so that's interesting the way רש"י Rashi frames that and
what רש"י Rashi has to say about it being עבודה זרה avodah
zarah that before you're מבטל mevatel it. תוספות Tosafot disagrees based on
a whole סוגיא. sugya. תוספות Tosafot says we're talking about an עבודה
זרה avodah zarah גוי goy after he was מבטל mevatel it and
that's why it's not a problem. But before he was מבטל mevatel
it, it's still a problem. That's תוספות's Tosafot position. I want to
say just one other thing about עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Yeah whatever,
we're not גוזר gozer אחר ביטול achar bittul לפני ביטול. lifnei bittul.
Fine. It's not so פשיטא pshita also because תוספות Tosafot quotes a
whole סוגיא sugya and this gets to the רש"י Rashi point about
why לכתחילה lechatchila not use it. Like, or how about can I
use for example a שופר shofar of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Is
it a problem that using something that was used for עבודה זרה
avodah zarah is invalid to do a מצווה mitzvah with? Not because
it technically doesn't count as a shoe because of כתותי מיכתת שיעוריה
katutei mekatat shiurei and it's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Maybe because it's
inappropriate to use as a מצווה mitzvah object. So תוספות Tosafot discusses
that whole discussion and he also assumes that whatever we say about
a שופר shofar we're going to say about a חליצה chalitzah shoe
in terms of thinking about it as a מצווה mitzvah object. So
that's another interesting point about, right, how much are we conceptualizing this
as a ritual מצווה. mitzvah. רש"י Rashi saying that we apply מצוות
לאו ליהנות ניתנו mitzvot lav lehennot nitnu and don't worry about איסורי
הנאה, issurei hana'ah, so that leads to a קולא. kula. תוספות Tosafot
saying that if there's a problem with מצווה mitzvah objects that were
involved in עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right, that we would not sort
of be able to use this because this is also a type
of a מצווה mitzvah object. For example, there's a principle about, right,
about מצווה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah. Let's say you stole the
shoe. Would you be יוצא yotzei if you used it or would
you say, oh no, מצווה הבאה בעבירה? mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah? Okay, so
that's a really interesting question about conceptualizing this as... it's not so
clear... conceptualizing this as a מצווה mitzvah or more as a type
of a דיני אבן העזר dinei Even HaEzer type of transaction.
So רש"י Rashi would...
רש"י Rashi
would מכשיר makhshir a שייטל shaitel from India and תוספות Tosafot wouldn't.
Alright, מורי ורבנן. mori verabbanan. Yes.
Is there a contradiction in this תוספות Tosafot you just described? One
that he already מבטל... mevatel...
no, he tries to figure out why it's not a problem. He
says, what do you mean?
I thought you said that
the שופר shofar and shoe would not be allowed.
Well, he treats them in a similar category, meaning whether they do
work or not is based on other סוגיאות. sugyot. But the point
is that he applies the same... the same principle to them, like
it's an issue of using a מצווה mitzvah object. What's the conclusion?
Yeah it depends... yeah exactly. Alright, so... alright, now what about the
זקן עשאו לכבודו? zaken asau lichvodo?
Why is that not... doesn't work? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
ליה רב פפא לאביי: amar lei Rav Papa le'Abaye: מאי שנא זקן
עשאו לכבודו? mai shena zaken asau lichvodo?
Why is a shoe used for a... for a shroud
not good for a corpse?
Even if it's a totally legitimate shoe.
It was a shoe before...
yeah, דלאו להילוכה עביד. delav lehilocha avid. It's not made for walking.
להילוכה. lehilocha. Right, it's made... that would be the case... it was
made specifically for the corpse. There's an... there's an industry out there
that produces shroud shoes. Okay, so they're not made for walking, so
even... so therefore they don't count as a shoe. Okay? So he
says if that's true, דבי דינא נמי, debei dina nami, the shoe
used by the בית דין Beit Din as well... I want to
make a pause here and acknowledge that before we had remember רב
יוסף Rav Yosef and אביי Abaye says give me your shoe and
whatever. Until now we're just assuming these are the normal shoes people
wear. You might come up with criteria but the assumption I think
would be that 90% of the time people would naturally be wearing
these shoes anyway. Now you're getting what is much more reflecting our
reality, בית דין Beit Din had a חליצה chalitzah shoe. You're going
to see that, right? So that is fascinating that already at this
time בית דין Beit Din has a חליצה chalitzah shoe that they
use. So then he says, if that's true,
דבי דינא נמי, debei dina nami, the... the
בית דין Beit Din shoe as well, דלאו להילוכה עביד, delav lehilocha
avid, who walks in the בית דין Beit Din shoe? We only
use the בית דין Beit Din shoe for doing the מצווה mitzvah
of חליצה chalitzah with. This is our special holy חליצה chalitzah shoe,
so it's not made for walking, it's made for doing the מצווה
mitzvah of חליצה. chalitzah. You got... it's a great irony, right? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה, amar lei, no, אילו משאיל ליה
שלוחא דבי דינא מי קפיד עליה דיינא? ilu mash'il lei shulcha debei
dina mi kapid alei dayana? Let's say the שליח shaliach of בית
דין Beit Din say, you know, he... he wanted to borrow the
חליצה chalitzah shoe, would the דיינים dayanim be... you know, be upset?
No, of course they'd let him borrow the חליצה chalitzah shoe! Which
is like... really they would?
I was just wondering if you wanted to borrow the shroud shoe?
Yeah, anyway. So therefore since, exactly,
since, since in ספרד Sefard you can walk with this, just למעשה
le-ma'aseh we choose not to walk with it, whereas the shroud shoe,
I don't know. It seems like a real better question than an
answer, but it is really fascinating that they would have a whole
חליצה chalitza shoe set aside, and you know, then it raises the
ironic, the irony that nobody is wearing, you know, it's such a
holy shoe that nobody wears it.
Yes? But this seems to imply that like let's say it was
the מת'ס meis's own shoe from beforehand?
Yeah, that's fine.
No, but I mean, but don't we say that
like it's אסור לכבודו assur lichvodo means it was made
for that purpose?
I know, but I'm saying that like if it wasn't, like if
it was his own shoe then used it for a shroud, then
you can like borrow it from the מת meis so to speak,
and then use it for חליצה? chalitza? I mean like...
All right, that gets back to the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah question.
Fine, but fine, that's fine. You're asking about a hypothetical that you
created, okay, the גמרא Gemara hasn't even discussed that case. But anyway,
that's an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah question, yeah.
If you read that the גמרא Gemara did not, did not say
is that maybe the shoe was אף על פי שלא נעשה לכבודו
af al pi shelo na'aseh lichvodo is one of those shoes that
isn't a real shoe? Right.
But then it wouldn't be a חידוש, chiddush, then we've already, then
we've dealt with that category already, you know. So, but right, once
it frames it the way it did, but you know, that's why
it, you know, that's why it was רב אשי Rav Ashi who
gave that framing and therefore that framing was challenged. That's exactly it.
You could have explained it otherwise and you wouldn't have had this
problem. Okay, so משנה. Mishna. חלצה בלילה, chaltzah balaylah, if she did
it at night, חליצתה כשירה, chalitzatah kesheira, it's good. רבי אליעזר פוסל,
Rabbi Eliezer posul, Rabbi Eliezer says it's invalid. בשמאל, bishmol, if it
was with the left. Now, left hand or left leg? Okay, so
there's a whole question about also how the woman does it, but
the, but the woman doesn't even have to use her hands; there
were cases if let's say she doesn't have hands, use her teeth.
So it means that it's on his left leg. חליצתה פסולה, chalitzatah
pesulah, it's invalid. רבי אליעזר מכשיר. Rabbi Eliezer machshir. So before we
said you could use a left shoe, but that was a left
shoe on the right leg. Using the left leg is assumed to
be invalid. Interesting debate in the פוסקים poskim about a lefty, okay,
and whether a lefty uses the right leg or the left leg,
or you have to do both to play it safe, or both
at the same time according to one opinion, I kid you not.
Anyway, well, everything, every single opinion out there, every single possibility. As
opposed to a לולב.
lulav. All right, לימא ובהא קמיפלגי, leima uv'ha kamifligi, let's say the
debate of tonight is the following debate. דמר סבר מקשינן ריבים לנגעים,
demar savar makshinan rivim lenegaim, we connect court cases, or like, you
know, ריב riv is like
litigation to issues of צרעת, tzara'as, נגעים. negaim. ומר סבר לא מקשינן
ריבים לנגעים, umar savar la makshinan rivim lenegaim,
we don't. Now, what פסוק pasuk is it? על פיהם
יהיה כל ריב וכל נגע. al pihem yihyeh kol riv vechol nega.
So it compares the בית דין Beis Din or כהנים kohanim whatever,
who decide all cases of litigation and נגעים, negaim, צרעת. tzara'as. Now
צרעת tzara'as we know is only ביום, bayom, in the day, that
the declaration of the כהן kohen is only day. ביום הראות בו
הכהן יטמא, bayom hira'os bo hakohen yitma, or what is it? הבשר
יטמא. habasar yitma. Anyway, so it's a day. So do we say
that cases of litigation also are only on the day or not?
Now, this is fascinating because why are you putting חליצה chalitza in
the litigation category? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says, right, רש"י Rashi says, חליצה, chalitza, the first narrow line of
רש"י, Rashi, דין הוא דגבי כתובתה, din hu degavi kesuvatah, it has
a דין din element because she collects her כתובה kesuvah as a
result. I would have said it has a דין din for the
reason I said because it's sort of like a transactional type of
a thing, you know, it defines their legal status and whether they're
connected to one another or not, it doesn't mean they're litigating, but
it's still within that similar type of an interpersonal status category, and
so on. But anyway, so get our issue of do you see
it as like a מצוה mitzvah or do you see it more
as like דין din is very relevant because here we're putting it
automatically in the ריב riv category. And the question is does it
need יום yom the same way נגעים negaim need יום? yom? But
of course if that's true it would be a general question whether
דיני ממונות dinei mamonos needs יום, yom, so that can't really be
that global type of a question. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: לא, דכולי עלמא לא מקשינן ריבים לנגעים. lo, d'chulei alma la
makshinan rivim lenegaim. Everybody agrees you don't make a general connection of
like, you know, litigation and דיני ממונות dinei mamonos to נגעים. negaim.
דאי מקשינן, de-ee makshinan, were we to have done that really in
a full way, אפילו גמר דין בלילה נמי לא, afillu g'mar din
balaylah nami lo, you wouldn't even be able to end a court
case at night. והלכתא v'hilchasa is that when you come to דיני
נפשות dinei nefashos it has to begin in the day and end
in the day, not the same day, but the proceedings
have to only be in the daytime, whereas by דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos once it starts in the day it can continue into the
night and the גמר דין g'mar din can be at night. So
therefore that then is going to provide our question of how to
frame this. So let's take a look.
ובהא קמיפלגי, uv'ha kamifligi, here is the debate. מר סבר חליצה כתחילת
דין דמיא, mar savar chalitza k'techilas din damya, חליצה chalitza is like
the beginning of a process and therefore it has to be in
the day, ומר סבר חליצה כגמר דין דמיא, umar savar chalitza k'gmar
din damya, it's like the end of a process. Now, the גמרא
Gemara says absolutely nothing about why it would say one way or
the other. Presumably the reason to say beginning is because this is
the, we haven't had anything that preceded the חליצה, chalitza, this is
the first they're coming to the court to have the חליצה. chalitza.
Why is it the end? You could say one of two ways.
Initially I was thinking that maybe because, right, the marriage sort of
started it and this is a continuation of the marriage and the
ending of the marriage and so on, but I thought there's an
easier reason. The גמר דין gmar din is basically when the בית
דין beis din proclaims their decision and the effect of the judgment
is made, right? So it says חייב, chayav, if that then would
be a גמר דין. gmar din. You owe the guy a hundred
dollars or you're פטור. patur. So here also the effect of what's
going on, you know, the change of her status is created during
this act of חליצה, chalitza, so it has in it the exact
same, it's the beginning and the end all happening at the same
time. Said you look at it as the end, you look at
it as the beginning. All right, so anyway, so that's the question
about whether it can be at night or not. Yes.
If יבום yibum is performed instead of חליצה, chalitza, the כתובה kesubah
of the former husband then becomes the כתובה kesubah of the יבמה?
yevamah?
Yes, yes, yes. Of the יבמה, yevamah, right, she meaning she, yes.
Right, and then of course she collects from which status she collects
it from, you know, yeah.
So I would have thought that you know, you would have said
the reason why it can't be done at
night—no, wait a minute, I'm not sure I understand you. She still
has with her כתובה kesubah is still on her dead husband's estate,
but, but if the dead husband's estate runs out and then the
second husband dies or whatever, then she can collect from the second
husband's estate.
The second husband, the יבם, yavam, he
doesn't write a new כתובה? kesubah? Correct, yeah.
See, I would have thought that you know, they might have tried
to learn it that it says here לעיני, le-einei, he has to
see it, it can only be done during the day.
No, that's, you know,
I mean maybe, even סומא suma we said was okay, or at
least if she was סומא, suma, now if they were... okay, anyway.
So the משנה Mishnah says it could have... okay. It's really ציצית
tzitzis we say—yeah, but that's because it's a דין din in the
בגד. beged. Anyway. All right, the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבה
בר חייה
קטוספאה, Rabba bar Chiya Katuspa'ah, okay, so a certain from קטוספאה, Katuspa'ah,
this רבה בר חייה. Rabba bar Chiya. עבד עובדא, avad uvda,
he did a חליצה chalitza case במוק, be-mok, first he used this
מוק mok which was this like hard felt which we said before
was okay but it's not your standard sandal. וביחידי, u-vi-yechidi,
alone, there was no בית דין, beis din, that's the first we're
hearing that, we heard of three, five, we've never heard of the
possibility of less than three. ובלילה, u-va-laila, and at night. So אמר
שמואל, amar Shmuel, so he's really gone out on a limb here.
So שמואל Shmuel says כמה רב גובריה, kama rav guvrei, how great
he is, רש״י Rashi said he sort of said it sarcastically as
a criticism. Oh, look how great this guy is, he's so great
that he can rely on all these דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. דעבד
כיחידאה, de-avad ke-yechida'ah,
he relied on these דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי קשיא, mai kashya, what's bothering שמואל? Shmuel? אי במוק, ei
be-mok, if it's because of this felt shoe, סתמא תניא, stama tanya,
we taught that yesterday, we said that this felt shoe was okay
and it was a סתם ברייתא. stam brayta. So it's not a
דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. אי לילה, ei laila, if it's night, סתמא
תניא, stama tanya, so that's taught in our משנה, Mishnah, it's the
סתם stam position of the משנה, Mishnah, even though there's a debate
of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's still the סתם stam position. אלא
יחידי קא קשיא ליה, ela yechidi ka kashya lei,
he's bothered with the idea that he did it without a בית
דין, beis din, right? Until now we've been saying three or five,
we haven't even heard anybody who says that you could do it
without a בית דין. beis din. היכי עביד כיחידאה, heichi avid ke-yechida'ah,
how could he do
it by a יחיד? yachid? יחידאה קתני לה, yechida'ah katani lah, that's
only a דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. דתנן, de-t-nan, we taught a משנה,
Mishnah, there's a משנה Mishnah that's going to be on our עמוד
ב׳. amud beis. חלצה בשנים, chaltza bi-shnayim,
if there was only two as part of the בית דין, beis
din, או בשלושה ונמצא אחד מהם קרוב או פסול, o bi-shlosha ve-nimtza
echad mei-hem karov o pasul, one of them was invalid, so it
basically became
two, חליצתה פסולה, chalitzasa pesula, it's
invalid. רבי שמעון ורבי יוחנן הסנדלר מכשירים, Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabbi Yochanan ha-Sandlar
machshirim, and רבי שמעון ורבי יוחנן הסנדלר
Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabbi
Yochanan
ha-Sandlar was weighing in on חליצה, chalitza, oh that's a good point.
ומעשה באחד שחלץ בינו לבינה, u-ma'aseh be-echad she-chalatz beino le-veinah,
there was a story about a certain person who did חליצה chalitza
only between him and the sister-in-law, בבית האסורים, be-veis ha-asurim,
and it was in prison, so there was no בית דין beis
din around. ובא מעשה לפני רבי עקיבא והכשיר, u-va ma'aseh lifnei Rabbi
Akiva ve-hichshir, and it was come to, it came to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and he said it was okay. So now we see
it's all sourced in a דעת יחיד, da'as yachid, there's an opinion
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says בדיעבד be-di'avad you don't need
a בית דין, beis din, which is pretty amazing because the פסוקים
psukim say לעיני הזקנים, le-einei ha-zekeinim, right? So there I mean, you
know, so it constantly emphasizes the presence of זקנים, zekeinim, like maybe
we could debate maybe one, maybe two, but to say בדיעבד be-di'avad
even none of them, that's a big חידוש chiddush and that's רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So anyway, it's a דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. So
what's this רבה בר חייה Rabba bar Chiya doing going like this
דעת יחיד? da'as yachid? ואמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן
אין הלכה כאותה הזוג, ve-amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman
ein halacha ke-osah ha-zug, we don't rule like רבי שמעון ורבי יוחנן
הסנדלר. Rabbi Shimon and Rabbi Yochanan ha-Sandlar. So here it is that
there are, you know, two of them maybe, but we don't rule
like that and it's sourced in a דעת יחיד, da'as yachid, what's
he doing ruling like them?
הכשיר, hichshir, does it mean לכתחילה le-chatchila or בדיעבד? be-di'avad?
No, this is בדיעבד. be-di'avad.
So then I also, so then I also why can he be
upset? Like, why is he doing so many things בדיעבד?
be-di'avad? Well, that's, תוספות Tosafos asks that, anyway he should have been
upset that he's doing all this בדיעבד be-di'avad stuff, but he was
asking a bigger question, he doesn't like it when people go by
דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. בדיעבד, לכתחילה, be-di'avad, le-chatchila, somebody else would be
bothered by that, for him he's concerned what's entitling him to just
go like a דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. ואי בעית אימא וכולהו נמי
יחידאה קתני להו, ve-i ba'is eima ve-chulhu nami yechida'ah katani lehu, and
if... I could even tell you more than that. It's not just
the לילה Layla with a דעת יחיד. das yachid. All these three
things in the end are sourced in דעת יחיד. das yachid. So
what do you mean? דתניא d'tanya we learned in a ברייתא: braitah:
אמר רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi, אני ראיתי
את רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע ani ra'isi es Rabbi Yishmael ben Elisha
שחלץ במוק ביחידי ובלילה. shechalatz b'moke b'yachidi uv'layla. So here's a report
of this רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע Rabbi Yishmael ben Elisha that did
exactly these three things. Right? That he did it—or רבי Rabbi. יוסי—רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי is telling it over—he did it with his felt
garment, without a בית דין, beis din, and at night. So you
see the—that all of these things might be in the end sourced
in a דעת יחיד. das yachid. Now, what does that mean להלכה?
l'halacha? You know, presumably there was no reason to question the earlier
פסקים psakim about the case about מוק moke and לילה, layla, but
nevertheless certainly the issue about a בית דין יחיד beis din yachid
is—is very much like, you know, a דעת יחיד. das yachid. But—but
in the end the other two positions might be sourced in that,
but not clear that that would mean we should really question it
להלכה. l'halacha. Yes, though?
Yeah, do we treat the phrase אין הלכה כ—its ein halacha k
meaning in Hebrew—the same way we treat הלכתא, hilchesa, like as a
later, you know...
No, first of all this is quoted specifically in the name of
an אמורא, amora, אמר רב נחמן. Amar Rav Nachman. Yeah. No, this
is much—first of all הלכתא, hilchesas, some הלכתא hilchesas are סבוראים, Savoraim,
not all of them are, but anyway, but this is, yeah, but
this is clearly earlier than that.
Yeah. רבה בר חייא תוספאה—is Rabba bar Chiya Tosfa'ah he the son
of the רב חייא Rav Chiya who worked with Rabbi...
you're asking the wrong person. Okay, so yes.
It's interesting because I just—רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי's Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi
always the one who's always evidence-based, like he's the one who says
"And I even saw the ציצית..."
tzitzis... That's a good point, right.
He's always bringing like, "I saw this happen."
Right, right, that's a good point. Alright, let's move on.
Everything's okay. בשמאל חליצה פסולה, B'smol chalitzah pesulah, so the left leg
it's not good, but then again there's a position of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that it is good. מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai ta'ama d'rabbanan?
What's the reason that the Rabbis say no good? It doesn't say
"right" in any way in the תורה Torah by this. אמר עולא
ילפינן רגל רגל ממצורע. Amar Ulla: Yalfinan regel regel mimitzora. By the
מצורע, mitzora, because you do this whole ritual with his right leg
when you're coming to be מטהר metaher him and it says רגל
הימנית, regel hayemanit, or his right foot. So here too... right. So
we learn it
out: מה להלן ימין אף כאן ימין. Mah lehalan yamin, af kan
yamin. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer לא יליף רגל רגל ממצורע. lo yalif
regel regel mimitzora. We don't learn out "right foot" from here—from there
to here. והתניא, V'hatanya, it's taught in a ברייתא: braitah: רבי אליעזר
אומר מנין לרציעה שבאוזן הימנית? Rabbi Eliezer omer: minayin l'ritzia shebe'ozen hayemanit?
How do you know in another case where it doesn't mention whether
right or left, that you do the piercing of the ear for
the slaves, how do you know it's the right
ear? נאמר כאן אוזן, Ne'emar kan ozen, it says here "ear", ונאמר
להלן אוזן, v'ne'emar lehallan ozen, and it says by the מצורע mitzora
"ear", by putting the blood on the right ear. מה להלן ימין
אף כאן ימין. Mah lehallan yamin, af kan yamin. So if he's
going to learn from מצורע mitzora to slave, he might as well
learn from מצורע mitzora to
חליצה. chalitzah. אמר רבי יוסף בר יוסף אמר יוחנן מוחלפת השיטה. Amar
Rabbi Yosef bar Yosef amar Yochanan muchlefet hashita. Fine, reverse the positions.
Right, that in one of—that basically have רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer consistent.
Presumably—not clear which way to begin with—but presumably have him say in
both places that you use the right and be the רבנן Rabbanan
the ones that argue. רבא
אמר לעולם לא תיהפך. Raba amar: l'olam lo tehipach. Don't reverse the
positions. אוזן אוזן מופני. Ozen ozen mufni. He's prepared to learn out
the case of "ear" because the ear's extra. It says ear, you
know, too many times
in—by the case by the slave. It says it extra times which
allows us to learn it out. רגל רגל לא מופני. Regel regel
lo mufni. There's not an extra time it says the word "foot"
here by חליצה. chalitzah. And you can look at the פסוקים psukim
and decide why the גמרא Gemara assumes one is extra and one
is not. And if it's not extra, you can't learn it out.
So the גמרא Gemara says: וכי לא מופני מאי פירכא איכא? V'chi
lo mufni mai pircha ika? Even if it's not—if it's not extra,
what question do you have? Because the basic point is, you can
make a גזירה שוה gezeira shava even if the words are not
open, or they're not open on both sides. Maybe one of the
words is doubled but the other one isn't. Or you don't understand—the
גזירה שוה gezeira shava you have to link from two places. So
do you need both words to be extraneous words or only one
of them to be an extraneous word? How does that work? So
anyway, here's a case where it's assumed that by the case of
the מצורע mitzora the words are extraneous, but are they extraneous in
the other place? By the אוזן ozen by the עבד eved or
by חליצה chalitzah to allow—I said extraneous, I shouldn't say—I said superfluous,
anyway. Are they extra? Excuse me, I didn't mean extraneous. Are they
extra? Redundant? Thank you. So it's assumed that they're redundant in the
case by מצורע, mitzora, but are they also redundant in the case
by עבד eved or what do you call it, or חליצה? chalitzah?
So we say: Oh, if it's redundant by עבד, eved, both words
are extra. At both endpoints we can make it. But if it's
not—but by חליצה chalitzah it's not redundant. So now the גמרא Gemara
says: One minute, even if it's not redundant, or not redundant in
both places, you're allowed to make a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. The
only difference between whether it's redundant in both places or not is
whether it can withstand a challenge. So what type of a challenge
would you have here that would need to be withstood? Why not,
alright, it's not redundant, but nevertheless let's just make the link. מאי
פירכא איכא? Mah pircha ika? What challenge do you have? So איכא
למפרך: ika l'mifrach: You
can ask: מה למצורע
שכן טעון ארז עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת. Mah l'mitzora sheken ta'un
erez, eitz erez, v'eizov, v'shani tola'as. Give me a break! מצורע
Mitzora has a lot more in terms of the ritual, right? So
you need all this other special stuff, so you need the right
ear. But חליצה chalitzah or the slave doesn't have a big ritual.
So, so מצורע *metzora* that has all of these criteria of exactly
the objects used and so on, it might demand also the right
ear, the right foot, but that doesn't necessarily mean that that's going
to be what's demanded by חליצה chalitza *chalitza*. Yes.
Are you suggesting
that in terms of the hermeneutics, the strongest גזירה שוה *gezeira shava*
is one where there's two redundancies, less so one, and the weakest
גזירה שוה *gezeira shava* where there's no redundancy?
Yes, that is absolutely correct. You could apply
that classification. Alright, so, okay, now moving on. But the הלכה halacha
*halacha* is we do say right, and as I said, there's a
fascinating question about what to do about lefties. Okay, it's also one
of the interesting areas of הלכה halacha *halacha* where righty and lefty
is important in terms of your feet as opposed to, you know,
righty lefty legwise as opposed to handwise. You know how they test
for it? Like, I think one of the ways they test—what? No,
they say stand still and now start walking, and which is the
foot you start with, right? So, so then the פוסקים poskim *poskim*
as opposed to like right-handed, you're like, could be which hand you
write with, but you know sometimes people are trained or whatever. Also
like throw somebody something, see which hand they intuitively jump out to
catch it with.
Kicking a ball when it's...
That too. Anyway, this then becomes an interesting discussion, then becomes an
interesting discussion in the פוסקים poskim *poskim*, particularly רב עובדיה יוסף *Rav
Ovadia Yosef*, a contemporary פוסק *posek* where everybody goes into the army,
which is that if in the army you were trained to, how
do they train you in the army, to always put forward one
foot first? Which one is it? I forget. Is it the right
or the left?
The marching chant is left, right, left.
Left, right, left. So if they train you in the army to
put the left foot forward first, is that to make you into
a lefty for laws of חליצה chalitza. *chalitza*? So there's a whole
תשובה *teshuva* of רב עובדיה יוסף *Rav Ovadia Yosef* about that. Okay,
so, and then you have to decide what you do with a
lefty, whether it's the left foot or the right foot. Okay, next
משנה Mishnah. *mishna*. חלצה ורקקה *chaltza verakeka*, she did, now we're going
to get to there's three components, right? Removes the shoe, spits, and
the reciting of the verses. So we're going to go through which
of them is מעכב me'akev *meakev*. חלצה ורקקה *chaltza verakeka*, she removed
the shoe and she spat, אבל לא lo, קראה *aval lo kara*,
she did not read the verses, חליצתה כשרה *chalitzata keshera*, that's kosher.
Okay, we'll see why. קראה ורקקה *kara verakeka*, she read the verses
and she spat, אבל לא חלצה *aval lo chaltza*, she didn't remove
the shoe, חליצתה פסולה chalitzasa pesula *chalitzata pesula*, it's invalid. There's a
reason it's called חליצה chalitza *chalitza*. חלצה וקראה *chaltza vekara*, she removed
the shoe and she said the verses, אבל לא רקקה *aval lo
rakeka*, she didn't spit, רבי Rabbi אליעזר אומר omer חליצתה פסולה *Rabbi
Eliezer omer chalitzata pesula*, it's invalid, רבי Rabbi עקיבא אומר חליצתה כשרה
*Rabbi Akiva omer chalitzata keshera*, so it's good. So the debate is,
everybody agrees בדיעבד bedieved *bedieved* you don't need to do the recital,
okay, because we're going to see a פסוק *pasuk* and it says,
you know,
it says and obviously why you're there.
Because the recital is more words, well not only that, but the
recital is more words, it's less of an act. So that everybody
agrees בדיעבד bedieved *bedieved* it's not מעכב me'akev *meakev*. The question is
about the spitting. So let's see what the debate of רבי Rabbi
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and רבי Rabbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is about the
spitting. Wait, let's finish the משנה Mishna, *mishna*. If there's no verbal...
Well no, we said before that the
דיינים *dayanim* have to be
somewhat knowledgeable so that they can
do the recite after me. אמר לו רבי Rabbi, אליעזר *amar lo
Rabbi Eliezer*, Rabbi Eliezer said to Rabbi Akiva—Rabbi Eliezer is the one
that
says you need to do the spitting—ככה יעשה kacha ye'aseh, *kacha yeaseh*,
this is what shall be done, which is כל דבר שהוא מעשה
מעכב me'akev, *kol davar shehu maaseh meakev*, anything that's an act is
מעכב me'akev. *meakev*. So this is where we also learn that the
reciting isn't מעכב me'akev. *meakev*, because it's not a יעשה *yeaseh*. Raises
interesting questions whether דיבור *dibbur* is מעשה *maaseh* or not, right? So
that's a fascinating issue in תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* brings in some of
that discussion, okay, whether דיבור *dibbur* is considered like an act or
not. But here the משנה Mishna *mishna* is assuming it's not. So
I get why reciting isn't מעכב me'akev *meakev* because it says ככה
יעשה *kacha yeaseh*, that's only speech. But spitting is an act. אמר
לו רבי Rabbi עקיבא *amar lo Rabbi Akiva*, Rabbi Akiva said back
to him, משם ראיה *misham raya*, from there you want to bring
a proof? ככה יעשה לאיש *kacha yeaseh laish*, this is what shall
be done to the man. כל דבר שנעשה באיש *kol davar shenasa
baish*, anything done to the man. So removing the shoe is doing
to him. Spitting in front of him is not doing to him,
it's doing in front of him. If she spat on him, maybe
that'd be different. But she spat in front of him and it's
not יעשה לאיש *yeaseh laish*. Okay, החרש שנחלץ *hacheresh shenichlatz*, so that's
one debate about whether spitting is מעכב me'akev *meakev*. החרש שנחלץ והחרשת
שחלצה *hacheresh shenichlatz vehachereshet shechaltza*, if a חרש cheresh *cheresh* did, had
his shoe removed, or the woman was a חרשת chereshet *chereshet*, and
חולצת לקטן *vecholetzet lekatan*, or if she removed the shoe of a
minor, חליצתה פסולה *chalitzata pesula*, it's invalid. So for the minor, she
can wait till he grows up, although it's interesting the משנה Mishna
*mishna* doesn't say that. But the other cases, it's not clear what
options exist, and I'll talk about that in a minute. קטנה ketanah
שחלצה *ketana shechaltza*, if she was a minor when she did it,
תחלוץ משתגדיל *tachlotz mishetagdil*, wait till she grows up. I'm not exactly
sure why it only mentions wait to grow up when she's a
minor as opposed to when he's a minor. ואם לא חלצה חליצתה
פסולה *veim lo chaltza chalitzata pesula*, if she did not redo it,
it remains invalid. חלצה בשנים או בשלושה *chaltza beshnayim o bishlosha*, now
this we quoted, if there's only פשיטא בשניים *pishita beshnayim*, I don't
know why I read that though, if there's only two... There's only
two if there's only two people in front and, you know, there
wasn't a full בית דין beis din. או בשלושה ונמצא אחד מהם
קרוב או פסול o bishlosha v'nimtza echad mehem karov o pasul or
three but one was invalid חליצתה פסולה it's invalid and it's like
Rabbi Yochanan סבירא ליה savra lei מכשירין machshirin they say it's okay
ומה דעבד עבד u'mah d'avad avad what happened happened שחלץ בינו לבינה
shechalatz beino l'veina there was a case it was all in private
nobody was around only one בבית האסורים bebeis ha'asurim in the prison
ובא מעשה לפני רבי עקיבא והכשיר u'va maase lifnei Rabi Akiva v'hichshir
Rabbi Akiva said it's fine. So not only do you not need
three and two and one whatever you don't need anyone
according to Rabbi Akiva. But we פוסקין pasken need a בית דין.
Now I want to say something about the idea about the חרש
cheresh and the וחרשת v'chereshet because we spoke the other day like
what are they supposed to do? How are they supposed to solve
the situation? And let's say she for example is not a חרשת
chereshet she's totally, you know, okay. The brother-in-law is a חרש cheresh
so she can't get remarried
and how's the situation supposed to resolve itself? So that's similar to
the discussion we had before about what do you do about a
guy that let's say is amputated above the knee. So so there
are scenarios I wanted I researched it a little bit and sometimes
when possible פוסקים try to say well maybe this is only דרבנן
d'rabbanan and therefore we don't say this in a case where there's
no other option. So some פוסקים will try to find if there's
some debates about things or whatever to make an argument that maybe
it's only דרבנן d'rabbanan we don't say it if there's no other
option. But or say that maybe even מדאורייתא mid'oraisa certain things were
only said when there were other options like other brothers etc. But
nevertheless the הלכה halacha does allow for cases where the woman's going
to remain an עגונה aguna where it's going to say it is
a דאורייתא d'oraisa and it's מעכב me'akev, and even if there's no
other option. So for example רש"י Rashi here says just to show
you where רש"י Rashi says it I mean רש"י Rashi explicitly makes
mention of this he says
the first narrow line of רש"י Rashi וחרשת שחלצה חליצתה פסולה v'chereshet
shechaltza chalitzasa pesula היא עצמה אינה נפטרת בחליצתה hi atzma eina nifteres
bechalitzasa she can't even do her own חליצה chalitza כדאמרינן לקמן בפרק
בית שמאי ked'amrinan lekaman beperek beis shamai ואין לה תקנה v'ein la
takana she has no option here okay
אלא ביבום ela b'yibum the only option would be is if she
would go ahead and do יבום yibum ואם רצו להוציא יוציא בגט
v'im ratzu lehotzi yotzi b'get if they don't want to remain married
יוציא בגט. yotzi b'get. Okay but how can he give her a
גט get if she's a...
okay so that
has to do with the whole thing about giving a גט get
to a חרשת chereshet or whatever. But the point I wanted you
to see is as the you know whereas the previous רש"י Rashi
חרש שחלץ חליצתה פסולה cheresh shechalatz chalitzasa pesula חרש cheresh it's no
good רש"י Rashi says לפוטרה במקום אח כשר lifotra b'makom ach kasher
it doesn't work if there's another brother around who can do it
there is which suggests that if there's another brother around who can't
if there's no other brother around then she's free because there's no
brother to do the חליצה. chalitza So this raises the question of
if it is literally impossible but you know does that mean that
okay then she's not bound right? Or does it mean that no
because think about it it would be one thing if the תורה
Torah only gave you the option of חליצה chalitza then you could
say if it's not possible how could the תורה Torah be demanding
it? But the תורה Torah isn't only give you the option of
חליצה chalitza it also allows you to do יבום yibum right? חליצה
chalitza is the way to get out of יבום. yibum. So it
allows for the possibility that there it would be not possible to
do יבום yibum not possible to do חליצה chalitza and the only
solution is יבום. yibum. Okay that even though it's not possible that
doesn't mean that you don't have to do it. All right so
we'll see some of that coming up as we continue. Let's look
at the גמרא. Gemara.
The מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum is on two people together right?
You have to
say...
right the תורה Torah frames it as the man's מצוה. mitzvah.
Well why does he have to say that?
כי ישבו אחים יחדיו ומת אחד מהם ובן אין לו לא תהיה
אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר יבמה יבא עליה
ki yeshvu achim yachdav u'meis echad mehem u'ven ein lo lo siheyeh
eishesh hameis hachutza l'ish
zar yevamah yavo aleha right it frames it on the man.
כי לא יחפוץ
האיש
ki lo
yachpotz ha'ish כי לא תעשה.
ki lo taaseh. But
anyway but yeah but the point is that since there is not
only the option of יבום yibum but certainly the way the תורה
Torah frames it that חליצה chalitza. is the way of getting out
of it so even in practice we sort of do חליצה chalitza
first nevertheless you know it because of the יבום yibum possibility it
makes it possible to say that this woman really חליצה chalitza isn't
an option which seems pretty you know shocking to us and her
so...
do we actually ever do יבום yibum like?
In ספרדי Sefardi communities they would sometimes I mean in theory it
would be possible in אשכנז Ashkenaz because if the man was single
but the practice has really developed in אשכנז Ashkenaz that we we
never do יבום yibum we always do חליצה.
chalitza But even in one of these cases?
I don't know that'd be no I would say in one of
these cases if there was not an option of חליצה chalitza. and
if let's say let's give an easier case the man wasn't married
and then we would either allow יבום yibum or we would allow
you know a יבום yibum followed by a גט get you know.
Okay אמר רבא Amar Rava השתא דאמרת hashta d'amart as said Rava
now that we said קריאה לא מעכבא kriya lo me'akva קריאה kriya
is not מעכב me'akev. because that was unanimous in the משנה. Mishna.
לפיכך אילם ואילמת שחלצו חליצתן כשרה lefichach ilem v'ilemes shechaltzu chalitzasan k'shira
if a mute person does חליצה chalitza, we never excluded them so
it's fine because you don't need to do קריאה. kriya. Okay תנן
tnan now let's challenge see if this is correct.
חרש שנחלץ וחרשת שחלצה. cheresh shenichlatz v'chereshet shechaltza. So fascinatingly, you know
we always assume חרש cheresh is automatically in the category of like
לאו בני דעה, lav benei de'ah, לאו בני חיובא, lav benei chiyuva,
people that are not sort of obligated in the law, okay, because
they're assumed to not have a full intellect. So that's obviously what
we would have said. For some bizarre reason the משנה, גמרא Gemara
is assuming that the problem of the deaf-mute is not the deaf
part, it's the mute part, and that the only problem is that
they can't speak, and therefore an אלם ileim would be the exact
same. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why are they invalid? לאו משום דלאו
בני קריאה נינהו? Lav mishum delav benei kri'ah ninhu? Is it because
they can't say the verses, and therefore an אלם ileim would be
the same? הגמרא Hagemara says, לא, no, משום דלאו בני דעה נינהו,
mishum delav benei de'ah ninhu, because they're not of full intellect. Again,
that's a whole story about the development of the category of חרש
cheresh and so on, but in the גמרא, Gemara, that's how they
categorize it, and that's why they're not בני חיובא, benei chiyuva, they're
not בני דעה, benei de'ah, they're like קטן katan and קטנה and
whatever, and that's why. But it has nothing but it's not because
you have to be able to to speak, even an אלם ileim
would be good. Wait one minute, אי הכי, ei hachi, says the
גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, אלם ואלמת נמי, ileim ve-ilemet nami, so
if that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara, say an אלם ileim and
an אלמת ilemet don't have דעת da'at because they how do we
know what they're thinking? They don't say anything. So you're right. So
אמר רבא, amar Rava, אלם ואלמת בני דעה נינהו. ileim ve-ilemet benei
de'ah ninhu. No, they have, they are of full intellect. ופומייהו הוא
דכאב להו, Ufumaihu hu de-che'av lehu, their mouth has a problem, okay?
They can't get the information out, but because they can get the
information in, right, that they can hear, so they're considered to be,
you know, and let's face it, people that were deaf-mute and weren't
able to hear, you know, to be deaf in a hearing society,
you know, the way often leads to them acting in ways, you
know, certainly in before that there was whole schools for the deaf
and so on, that, you know, weren't didn't exactly fit in, you
know, all the time with normal society and made people think that
they were not of a full intellect. So as opposed to people
that were hearing and just couldn't speak, so רבא Rava says those
there's no question, those are full intellect, they just can't speak, and
therefore they're not פסול pasul for חליצה chalitzah as opposed to חרש
וחרשת. cheresh ve-chereshet.
Yes, if I understand is when we say that the קריאה kri'ah
is מעכב, me'akev. are we being very literal? Like or like let's
say there's like they're talking, oh yeah, he doesn't you know what
I mean?
But nobody's saying it's מעכב. me'akev That's the thing. Even in this
discussion, the only question is do we exclude the person of an
אלם ileim and an אלמת? ilemet? Everybody agrees קריאה kri'ah is not
מעכב. Hold on.
But like our משנה says ולא קרא. velo kara. We mean they
didn't say literally these words over here? But like let's say they
were saying it?
I don't you mean like in translation, is it בכל לשון? be-chol
lashon? So fine, that's let's not worry about that right now. That's
a question, okay? Is it one of the things that are נאמרים
בכל לשון ne'emarim be-chol lashon or will a paraphrase work or whatever?
We'll worry about that, but right now we're not talking about that.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
So אלם ואלמת ileim ve-ilemet are fully בני דעה, benei de'ah, they
just can't speak, and therefore they're fine, and חרש וחרשת cheresh ve-chereshet
are excluded because they're more out of the category of בני דעה.
benei de'ah. Okay, that's one פשט. pshat. אלא הא, Ela ha, says
מאי, mai, says הא, ha, והאמרי דבי רבי ינאי, ve-ha-amrei devei Rabbi
Yannai, but how can you say that? Don't they say in the
school of רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, לפי שאינו באמר ואמרה, lefi she-eino
be-omar ve-omrah, that if you are mute, you and maybe he says
this to explain the משנה of חרש וחרשת, cheresh ve-chereshet, which is
fascinating because you should be aware there is opinions in the תנאים
Tanna'im and even a little bit in the גאונים, Geonim, but they
wind up getting sort of completely ignored להלכה, le-halacha, that a חרש
וחרשת cheresh ve-chereshet are בני דעה, benei de'ah, so which is very
important when the when that category starts to evolve in modern times,
you know, based on like I said, schools for the deaf and
a recognition that they are בני דעה. benei de'ah. So here you
have a position of רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai that says the reason
for them is not because they're not בני דעה, benei de'ah, the
reason is is because they're not able to say the word. So
on the one hand, it's a more positive categorization of חרש וחרשת,
cheresh ve-chereshet, but on the other hand that would have the effect
of excluding the אלם, ileim, the mute. Is everybody here with me
sort of what's going on? Okay. So he says, okay, so he
says look, he explains that חרש וחרשת cheresh ve-chereshet is because they
can't speak, not because they're not בני דעה. benei de'ah.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא כי איתמר דרבא אסיפא איתמר. ela
ki itmar de-Rava aseifa itmar. So the גמרא Gemara actually concedes the
point. You know what? You're right. רבא Rava would have actually we're
going to change what רבא Rava said, and רבא Rava will say
that a mute person cannot do חליצה. chalitzah. Even though you don't
have to say the words, you have to be able to say
the words. And that's the phrase אינו באמר ואמרה eino be-omar ve-omrah
means they're not in the category of being able to do the
recitation. And that excludes them. So even though you don't have to
say the words, you have to be able to say the words.
Okay, and what רבא Rava said was on the end of the
משנה. חרש שנחלץ וחרשת שחלצה והחולצת מן הקטן חליצתה פסולה, Cheresh she-ne-chelatz
ve-chereshet she-chaltzah ve-hachalotzet min ha-katan chalitzatah pesulah, that these deaf-mutes is invalid,
and we're going to decide like דבי רבי ינאי devei Rabbi Yannai
that that is not because they're not בני דעה, benei de'ah, that's
because they can't speak. And if that's the reason they're invalid because
they can't speak, אמר רבא, amar Rava, השתא דאמרת קריאה מעכבא, hashta
de-amarta kri'ah me'akeva, now that you're telling me that the that the
recitation is מעכב—if not the doing of the recitation, the ability to
recite is
מעכב—לפיכך אלם ואלמת שחלצו חליצתן פסולה, so similarly a mute person is
invalid. So this has the effect of expanding who's invalid for חליצה,
chalitzah a mute person, but interestingly by by assuming that fundamentally a
חרש cheresh is in a בר דעת bar da'at category.
מתניתין Matnitin to
Rabbi Zeira and the re-explanation of the Mishnah, so I don't get
it. We said you don't have to do the reciting, but now
we're saying that a חרש and חרשת are invalid not because they're
not בני דעה bnei de'ah but because they're not able to recite.
And similarly an אילם ilem is not able to recite or אילמת.
ilemet. So how could it be that you don't have to recite
but you have to be able to recite? So
the
Gemara says that's like Rabbi Zeira. ומתניתין U-matnitin to Rabbi Zeira, דאמר
de-amar Rabbi Zeira: כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו וכל שאינו
ראוי לבילה בילה מעכבת בו. kol ha-ra'uy le-bilah ein bilah me'akevet bo
v-chol she-eino ra'uy le-bilah bilah me'akevet bo. It's about a מנחה. mincha.
If you're bringing a מנחה, mincha, flour with oil, so the הלכה
halacha? is that the Torah describes the מנחה mincha as בלולה בשמן,
belulah ba-shemen, mixed with oil. That's the word בילה. bilah. Okay, but
בדיעבד if you don't mix it, it's okay. But if you have
so much flour that it's not possible to mix it, then it's
no good. Okay, so Rabbi Zeira is saying you sometimes don't actually
have to do something, but it has to have the potential of
being able to be done. Oh yeah. Now the question of course
is like when do we say that? Like okay, I don't have
to take the לולב lulav as long as I'm able to take
it, right? I don't have to put on תפילין tefillin as long
as I'm able to put it on. So what תוספות Tosafot points
out is, he doesn't sort of make this, spell this out a
lot, but the basic conceptually is if you're talking about the characteristic
of something, בלולה בשמן, belulah ba-shemen, you're not saying you must do
בילה. bilah. There's no verb there, it's an adjective, בלולה בשמן. belulah
ba-shemen. Then we could say it's enough that it's able to be
mixed. That makes us look at its character as בלולה בשמן. belulah
ba-shemen. If we say you must do this act, then we would
say then it'd be much harder to say oh, it's enough to
just have the potential to do it. Of course the problem with
it is that by חליצה chalitzah it actually says ואמר ואמרה, ve-amar
ve-amrah, it doesn't just say an אומר should be saying it. Okay,
but anyway as a general understanding of what this is about, if
you take a look at תוספות the very narrow two lines right
before it gets middle side, ואם תאמר ואמאי לא מעכבת והלא בכמה
מקומות כתיב בלולה במנחה מאפה תנור ושמן מחבת ומנחת נסכים כתיב טובא
בלולה ve-im tomar ve-amai lo me'akevet ve-lo be-chama mekomot ketiv belulah be-mincha
ma'afeh tanur ve-shemen machavat u-minchat nesachim kativ tuba belulah etc. etc. He
says ויש לומר, ve-yesh lomar, the third of the middle lines, דלא
משמעי עכובא כיון דלא כתיב ויבלול או ובללת לשון ציווי. de-lo mashma'ei
ikuva kivan de-lo ketiv ve-yivlol o u-bilaltah lashon tzivuy.
Okay,
so since it doesn't say you must or since it doesn't say
a verb I would say, it says it more as an adjective
as a descriptor, maybe it's enough that it has the potential. So
we're now saying that here, although again here it does say verbs,
that as long as they're, they don't have to do the reciting
because it says ככה יעשה, in the end only the act is
מעכב, but since it says ואמר ואמרה, ve-amar ve-amrah, we're going to
read that to say that בגברא bi-gavra they have to have the
ability to do it, and therefore a mute person cannot do it.
Okay,
so now the Gemara says like this, שלחו ליה דאבוה דשמואל, shalchu
leh de-avuhah de-Shmuel, they sent to the father of Shmuel: יבמה
שרקקה תחלוץ.
Yevamah she-rakakah
tachlotz. If a יבמה yevamah did just the spitting, she didn't do
anything else, she just did the spitting, so then she has to,
that invalidates her from ייבום. yibum. Even though obviously it's not good,
all she did was the spitting, she didn't do anything else, but
that was enough to invalidate her from ייבום. yibum. And now the
only option available to her is חליצה. chalitza Okay, מכלל, mikhlal, that
implies דאיפסלה לה מן האחין, de-ifsala lah min ha-achin, that so now
the Gemara is analyzing it, it implies that the spitting is enough
to invalidate her from the brothers, it's enough to prevent ייבום. yibum.
מני Mani? Who is this going like? אילמא Ilema Rabbi Akiva, if
it's Rabbi Akiva who says you בדיעבד you don't even have to
spit, השתא ומה דמקום מצווה דאיכא למימר מידי דהוי אימורין, hashta u-ma
de-makom mitzvah de-ika le-meimar midi de-havei emurin,
when it's actually you're doing the מצווה mitzvah of חליצה and you
have the ability to spit, you might say that in that case
spitting is necessary like by the burning of the אימורין emurin of
the sacrifice, that whether you need to do it to eat the
meat. That what do we say about the burning of the אימורין?
emurin? דכי ליתנהו, Dekhi lestinhu, if no of the אימורין emurin aren't
there they got טמא tamei they got lost, לא מעכבי lo me'akvi
you can go ahead and eat the meat without them. וכי איתנהו,
Vekhi itinhu, but when you do have the אימורין, emurin, מעכבי me'akvi
you can't eat the meat without them. So you might say spitting,
alright, if you're just doing spitting by itself or whatever, nothing. But
but but you know but when you actually have, you're doing the
act of חליצה and you have the potential of doing spitting and
you don't do it, maybe that's מעכב. And even so Rabbi Akiva
doesn't say that. Okay so he doesn't say even when you could
be in need to be doing spitting and you would say even
then he doesn't say it's מעכב. So for him you could say
spitting is like trivial, nothing. So for him certainly spitting should not
invalidate this woman, we don't even demand it even when we're doing
the מצווה mitzvah and it's possible. So in that case אמר רבי
עקיבא לא מעכבא, amar Rabbi Akiva lo me'akva, that Rabbi Akiva says
it's לא מעכבא lo me'akva when you're really doing the מצווה, mitzvah,
מאחין איפסלה? me'achin ifsala? Spitting will carry enough weight to invalidate? from
the brothers, אלא רבי אלעזר. Ella Rabbi Elazar. Fine, it's going to
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar who says spitting is necessary. All right, fine,
spitting is necessary, but nevertheless, ושני דברים המתירין נינהו. ushenei devarim hamatirin
ninhu. This is a case where you need two things to make
her מותר, mutar, the חליצה and the spitting. Right, there's two necessary
criteria. ושני דברים המתירין אין מעלין זה בלא זה. ushenei devarim hamatirin
ein ma'alin zeh belo zeh. So if you need two things, each
one by itself is meaningless. So therefore, now count of course you
could say דרבנן, D'rabonon, we have plenty of דרבנן, D'rabonon, but the
גמרא Gemara is saying I don't get it, spitting by itself, even
if it's necessary, is not sufficient, and therefore why does it have
the power to invalidate her from the brothers? So the גמרא's Gemara
answer is אלא לרבי, ella l'Rabbi, it's like רבי. Rabbi? דתניא, detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, כבשי עצרת, kivsei atzeret,
the lambs of the of the that are brought on שבועות, Shavuot,
okay, and you also bring it with loaves of bread. So the
הלכה is the loaves of the bread don't get קדושת הגוף kedushat
haguf like a קדושת קרבן kedushat korban until you are מקריב makriv
the lambs. Okay, so in that case, אין מקדשין הלחם אלא בשחיטה.
ein mikadshin halechem ella bishchitah. You have to שחט shacht them and
we're going to see not only שחיטה. shchita. כיצד, keitzad, how is
this? שחטן לשמן, shachtan lishmon, you did the right שחיטה, shchita, וזרק
דמן לשמן, vezarak daman lishmon, and the right זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam,
קידש הלחם, kidesh halechem, the bread is sanctified. שחטן שלא לשמן וזרק
לשמן, shachtan shelo lishmon vezarak lishmon,
but if one of those was not done properly, לשם, leshem, you
know, כבשי עצרת. kivsei atzeret. Either the שחיטה shchita was not correct
even though the זריקה zrika was, לא קידש הלחם, lo kidesh halechem,
it's not good. Now, שחטן לשמן וזרק דמן שלא לשמן, shachtan lishmon
vezarak daman shelo lishmon,
let's say that's when the שחיטה shchita was no good. Let's say
the שחיטה shchita was good because remember we emphasized שחיטה, shchita, so
let's say the שחיטה shchita was good, but the זריקה zrika was
not לשמן. lishmon. What's the הלכה? So in that case, קדוש ואינו
קדוש דברי רבי. kadosh ve'eino kadosh divrei Rabbi. רבי says you got
it halfway. Okay, what does halfway mean? So halfway means is that
it's פסול, pasul, I mean it has the קדושה kedusha of a
קרבן korban that has all the potential of being פסול pasul like
a קרבן, korban, and on the other hand you can't go ahead
and eat it, so it's sort of like the worst of both
worlds, okay, that's what רבי says, קדוש ואינו קדוש. kadosh ve'eino kadosh.
But okay, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר לעולם אינו קדוש עד שישחט
לשמן ויזרוק דמן לשמן.
Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Shimon omer le'olam
eino kadosh ad sheyishchat lishmon veyizrok daman lishmon.
No, it's either zero or a hundred, there's no fifty percent. So
how is this relevant? It's relevant by analogy. If רבי says you
need two things, שחיטה shchita and זריקה, zrika, what happens if you
have only one of them? So if you have only one of
them, is it zero or is it fifty percent? So there's an
idea of רבי that has an idea fifty percent. So for רבי,
within רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, if the spitting is מעכב and necessary,
then you got two criteria, and if you did only one of
them, is it zero or fifty? So רבי and רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar combined would say it's fifty percent, and therefore it's enough to
invalidate her on the brothers. Okay, we will end with this and
we are fully caught up. רבי?
Yes. zero not
fifty.